<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a Protestant of integrity to a principal peer of the realm now sitting in Parliament by way of animadversion on a letter from a person of quality to the same peer of the realm : occasioned by the present debate upon the penal laws.</title>
            <author>C. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D53</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26472</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09475559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09475559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1307:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a Protestant of integrity to a principal peer of the realm now sitting in Parliament by way of animadversion on a letter from a person of quality to the same peer of the realm : occasioned by the present debate upon the penal laws.</title>
                  <author>C. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: C.D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43230:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A Proteſtant of integrity, TO A <hi>Principal Peer</hi> of the Realm now ſitting in Parliament. BY Way of Animadverſion on a Letter from a Perſon of Quality to the ſame Peer of the Realm. Occaſioned by the preſent debate upon the Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43230:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43230:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER, From a Proteſtant of Integrity, unto a Principal Peer of the Realm, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Purpoſed not by my lines to intterrupt your purſuit of the important affairs in which you are ingaged; had not the unexpected boldneſs of a well-wiſher to the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> occaſioned theſe.</p>
            <p>Your conſtancy in, and zeal for the true Religion, (received and profeſſed in theſe Nations) will be your Lordſhips honour, no leſs then your care and compaſſion to conſciences pretendedly tender, not onely differing in circumſtances (which love to truth may indulge) but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting and diametrically oppoſite unto the ſubſtantials thereof, ſuch as are the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> for whom a pretended <hi>Perſon of quallity,</hi> hath preſumed to become an advocate, beyond what your Lordſhips Diſpoſition, his Majeſties Reputation, or our Kingdoms preſent complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (in which the reſtoring Prelacy is ſuſpected, and by ſome openly averred, to tend to a return to Popery) could dictate to men of any competent prudence.</p>
            <p>My Lord, publiquely to obſerve the Parliaments debates concerning the <hi>Penal Laws, is no peice of Policy;</hi> but this Gentlemans improvement thereof, ſeemeth to be little
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43230:3"/> ſhort of folly; ſuggeſting a propenſity to alter our eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion, and that the (now falling) Presbyter hath been and yet is the Papiſts onely opponent and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in which that party will not a little glory, as conceiving ſome thing of truth in their obſervation that our <hi>Litturgy and Prelacy, is very conſiſtent with the Maſs and Papacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Advocate repreſenteth his Popiſh party, by epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites, which cannot but move pitty, and in an eſtate which directeth duty for their releif and reſtoration if what he ſuggeſteth be found a verity.</p>
            <p>He calls them a poor diſtreſſed and deplorable party; <note place="margin">Pag. 1.</note> and my Lord, ſuch indeed they do ſeem to be; but wiſe men are not without fear, that on liberty to uncaſe they will appear more conſiderable, as thoſe who under all our late differing formes, have driven on the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques deſign, <hi>De propaganda fide,</hi> fomenting our late tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and commotions, <hi>Latet anguis in herbis,</hi> their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to hiſs unto the defaming of our eminent Martyrs, deriſion of our Religion, and demand of the liberty of their own driving on (in the late pamphlets boldly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into the World) diſpleaſure againſt, and depreſſion of the Presbyterians (who have much more pleadable in their behalf to propoſe them acceptable, then the preſent heat of our Revolutions will permit them to produce, or the Peers and reſtored Prelates of our Realm to ponder) are in my opinion no mean evidences thereof, for it is well known <hi>affected poverty, and voluntary affliction</hi> is not the leaſt part of this peoples <hi>piety and devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to their Eſtate he tels us (my Lord) this laſt hundred years, they have lain under <hi>a more bloody and inhumane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, then any before was hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of among Chriſtians.</hi> I muſt confeſs preſent evil ſeems unparralelled; and paſſion is a multiplying glaſs; but Sir, will not any ordinary obſerver ſee this advocate doth highly hyperbolize and in a ſullen fret like a ſubtile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apiſt, labour to delude by lies?</p>
            <p>My Lord, admitting (what principles of Juſtice cannot
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43230:3"/> admit) that their <hi>legal proſecution,</hi> were <hi>perſecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,</hi> is it not monſtrous to cry out, it is <hi>bloody and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> whilſt by known and ſtanding Laws declaring guilt and puniſhment; and that making many gradations and ſlows proceſs to the capital crime or ſhedding of their blood; but the ſuperlative words muſt appear ſuperlatively falſe; <hi>viz. That they have lain under the moſt bloody and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane perſecutions, that ever before was heard of among Chriſtians,</hi> for (my Lord) who that ever knew or heard of, the <hi>Heathen</hi> rage againſt <hi>Chriſtians, Arrians</hi> againſt the Orthodox, can give credit to this clamorous calumny; yea who ever heard of the Popiſh perſecution of Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albingenſes,</hi> the devaſtation of <hi>Merundal and Cabriers;</hi> The fiery perſecution in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the barbarous Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> with many the like doleful Tragedies, acted by the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, on no other cauſe but matter of opinion, and Religion, which they called Hereſie, and will not ſee for number and quality of patients, nature and variety, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and ſeverity of torments, ſlightneſs of cauſe and univerſality of Execution without Law or regard of age, ſex, dignity degree, (cutting down the tree, with the fruit thereof falling in the very act of execution) a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution much <hi>more bloody and inhumane,</hi> then what this <hi>perſon of quality</hi> complaineth of; who may be boldly challenged to make good his compariſon by making his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel for numbers of ſufferers, bloody inhumane ſufferings; to ſquare onely with the three Marian fiery years, and can chuſe, but conclude our Advocate judged by the age of his patients, not the kinds or degrees of their ſufferings; and ſure (my Lord) this Gentleman was wholly a ſtranger to the clemency of King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, Witneſſed by the <hi>eaſie compoſitions of Recuſants,</hi> and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>repreive and releaſe of Prieſts and Jeſuites;</hi> and I am ſure their reign will ſtrike far into his hundred years com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of; However (my Lord) an Hyperbole may be indulged in an advovate, when it is ſo notorious as in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43230:4"/> caſe, it cannot but return to the dammage of the Client.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I cannot but wonder, whilſt <hi>toleration of Popery</hi> is the thing pretended, that ſo great a liberty and on ſuch a ground, ſhould be required, and that as a duty, not courteſie, <hi>viz. That his Majeſty like another Cyrus, may be pleaſed to procure, that Iſrael may return and build up their T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple, and that becauſe the building is perpetual where God layeth the foundation,</hi> which whole requeſt is (my Lord) grounded on a bold <hi>petitio principii</hi> for they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who on good ground have been accounted <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> they challenge the priviledge of <hi>Syon,</hi> who are obnoxious to the doom of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and as ſuch, muſt expect <hi>Cyrus</hi> his oppoſition; <hi>For the Kings of the earth muſt hate the Whore.</hi> They pretend to be founded by God who make <hi>petrum petram,</hi> beyond the tenure of the the Goſpel, Commiſſion or ſcope of the Lords intention; when thoſe things are cleared, which they (but all others deny) take for granted; there will be a ground to pray not onely <hi>a liberty to uſe their Synagogile,</hi> but (as they Phraſe it) <hi>to build their Temple,</hi> and reſtore their Maſs, and (what is doubtleſs further in their intention) ruine all that diſſent from them; for (my Lord) it is a Scripture Maxime and an Eccleſiaſtical axiome, <hi>Sions riſe is Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is urged by way of <hi>Swada</hi> to this deſired liberty in the next Paragraph, ſignifieth very little, until <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> are rendred tolerable, by an Abjuration of intolerable principles and practices we ſhall eaſily aſſent to this Advocates Politiques, in point of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> and do believe, the <hi>Capital crime</hi> and puniſhment in the common Weal, as the <hi>chief cenſure</hi> in the Church fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt when made common, by being affixed to every light tranſgreſſion, and trivial defect; nor will I trouble your Lordſhip with tracing, or a tedious animadverſion of his hiſtorical obſervation of the clemency of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> indulgency of <hi>Aurelius,</hi> or connivance of <hi>Theodocius</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43230:4"/> and <hi>Gratianus,</hi> admitting them as true, his work is to make Papiſts ſquare with primitive Chriſtians, and maintain his inference, which he is well aware will be found a plain <hi>Non ſequitur</hi> on his premiſes, it is this <hi>a minori ad majus, how much more reaſonable will it appear to tolerate our brethren of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Religion, who are undeniably</hi> filii Chriſti, <hi>ſons of Chriſt by the mother Church, which we in</hi> England <hi>uſe to call the ſurer ſide, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, whatſoever the premiſes will allow, I muſt be bold to ſay, the inferences is ſtuffed with fancies, which cannot be admitted, in all the particulars of it; it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth with a plain <hi>petitio principii,</hi> under controverſie, yea, cleared in the negative.</p>
            <p>This Advocate (my Lord) challengeth the <hi>freedom</hi> of the Houſe, under a filial relation as <hi>brethren:</hi> He therefore affirmeth with confidence, <hi>The Roman Catholicks are unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably</hi> Filii Chriſti: But he dealeth wiſely in cleaving to the Baſtard pleas, <hi>on the Mothers ſide,</hi> leſt the very bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the claim ſhould provoke the family to whip them out of doors. Yet (my Lord) as undeniable as this Filial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation appeareth to him, it would be conſidered, whether their Mother hath not played the Harlot, and ſo they may be found children of Adultery, although living in Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, by our Law (not admitting the childe to be rightly fathered) covereth her ſin, and their ſhame.</p>
            <p>Again, it would be conſidered, whether the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath not given the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a bill of divorce, and branded her as <hi>the Mother of Whoredoms, ſpiritual</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Egypt, <hi>and</hi> Babylon; from whom all chaſte Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are charged to <hi>Separate</hi> with deteſtation, leſt they be defiled with her uncleanneſs: It is more then probable, that on a ſerious ſcrutiny, this Advocates impudent claim of the Papiſts ſonſhip to Chriſt, may be ſilenced with, <note place="margin">Hoſea 2.1,2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Plead with your mother, plead with her, ſhe is not my wife, neither am I her husband, &amp;c. I will not have mercy upon her children, for they be the children of Whoredomes; for their mother hath played the Harlot, ſhe that conceived them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th done ſhamefully.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43230:5"/>
            <p>Again, how came the <hi>maternity of the Chriſtian Church</hi> to be confined to any place, or peculiar people? Is not the wall of partition between Nations pulled down, and quite removed? When was <hi>Rome</hi> thus eſpouſed to Chriſt, that all <hi>filii Chriſti</hi> muſt be <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>on the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the ſurer ſide?</hi> As if none could be members of his Church, without being Provinces to the Roman Empire, and Proſelytes to their ſuperſtition. Why may not <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Antioch, Galatia,</hi> claim this Prerogative, as well as <hi>Rome?</hi> We may finde <hi>Rome</hi> conform to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by that name, as her Succeſſor; but that ſhe ſucceeded to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is a blinde bottomleſs ſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition: Yet we grant, the caſting out of the Jews, was the bringing in of the Gentiles; let this Contract, neceſſitating ſuch as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore were to <hi>Jewdaize,</hi> now to <hi>Romanize,</hi> or to renounce their relation to Jeſus Chriſt, be cleared. This is (my Lord) a moſt Popiſh brag, without any bottom, though this Advocate hath the confidence to tell your Lordſhip, <hi>That it is a verity undoubtable</hi> (ſo far as I could finde) <hi>that that Church was formerly the reverend Mother of Chriſtianiſm, and the moſt ancient Law-maker and Judge heretofore of all Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may (my Lord) ſee what is the toleration deſired for Roman Catholicks, how high they would build the Popes Temple, if <hi>Cyrus</hi> will give them liberty. <hi>Rome</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, if ſhe may not be the <hi>Queen and Miſtreſs of the World,</hi> to whom all muſt bow, as bound to her for their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being. But (my Lord) this Advocate ſeemeth better read in Roman Legends, then Scripture, or Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords; otherwiſe he would have found, <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.3.</note> the <hi>Law ſhould, and did go out of Sion, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> And (my Lord) from this ſeed do ſpring the ſons of Chriſt; in this place the Lord himſelf preached, hither were the Apoſtles confined, from hence they diſperſed themſelves through the world, hitherto the Chriſtians appealed as to the <hi>Law-maker and Judge of Religion. Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is (my Lord) called and known to be the <hi>Mother of us
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43230:5"/> all.</hi> If our ſonſhip to Chriſt be cognoſcible and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by our relation to any ſpecial place, as the <hi>Mother of Chriſtianiſm,</hi> we are bound (by natural affection) to go on Pilgrimage, and undertake the Holy War, for the Holy Land; or at leaſt, muſt have recourſe to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where <hi>Believers were firſt called Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, I will ſtand by the Hiſtorical demonſtration thereof, that Superſtition was made the ſum of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, and an univerſal Papacy affected, before <hi>Romes</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Motherhood became a mask of ſonſhip unto Chriſt, and Chriſtianiſm was found in our Iſland, before <hi>Auſtin, Romes</hi> proud, bloody, and ſuperſtitious Apoſtle came to plant.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, my Lord, admit we <hi>Romes</hi> Motherhood; muſt degenerated children or branches be tolerated? ſhall not ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be caſt out, and prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> loſe his birthright, though the one be undeniably the ſon of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and the other of <hi>Iſaac?</hi> Is it not our Saviours rule, <hi>Every branch that beareth not fruit, muſt be cut off?</hi> much more, that which beareth wilde fruit: Simple ſymbolical relation to Chriſt, will not avail to entrance into heaven, nor entertainment in the Church.</p>
            <p>My Lord, theſe premiſes being groundleſs, the inference is eaſily evaded; and admitting the Chriſtians liberty by the Heathen, Orthodox under the Arrians, Jews among the Venetians, and Moors among the Spaniards; yet it will not follow with any Emphaſis, that we ſhould <hi>much more tolerate our</hi> (degenerate, ſpurious) <hi>brethren of the Roman Religion;</hi> and the rather, becauſe their principles, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced practices, render them more unſociable then the very worſt of theſe, even deſtructive to Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
            <p>This exception (my Lord) is ſo legible, that it ſtared this Advocate in the face in the very penning of this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy: He ſeemeth to obviate and anſwer it in his next Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, in which his furious, freting terms do beſpeak him thereby pinched to the quick: he therefore ſtateth it in theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43230:6"/> angry expreſſions, <hi>It is a moſt falſe Propoſition, and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doubtleſs from gall and ſpleen, that Roman Catholicks are altogether conſociable, or that they cannot live with us, or any ſort of Proteſtants in one Kingdom and Commonwealth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out jars and tumults:</hi> And ſo in the height of rage he lets fly at the Presbyterians, and ſaith, <hi>This is blown from their mad, turbulent and preſumptuous pulpits,</hi> whom he purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with many invectives, throughout his whole book, as if they onely were his Antagoniſts.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I am not Advocate for the Presbyterians (the chief unhappy declining party among us) yet I cannot (in retired and ſerious thoughts) but wiſh the preſent violence and contempt poured on them, may be found to redound to the honour and good of our King and Kingdom: What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>tranſcendent power over Kings and States,</hi> ſome ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious men (cloathed with that appellation) might purſue; we cannot deny the generality of that party to have done His Majeſtie moſt eminent ſervice, and were they as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable in their Eccleſiaſticks, as they are ſound in their Politicks, they would be ranked among the beſt, moſt learned, and ſeriouſly pious of His Majeſties Subjects: To give them their due (which we ſay muſt not be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Devil) I finde <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf (who is deemed the moſt violent of them) in the very book for which he now ſuffers, ſo fully and plainly to aſſert his Majeſties Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Immunity from all humane condition (as to His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects allegiance) and co-action; and ſo fully ſquare in all his Politicks, that I cannot but queſtion the prudence (not to ſay the juſtice) of his ſo long and ſevere durance. But (my Lord) let theſe men be what they will, I am ſure the Presbyterians loſe not, nor doth our Church gain by theſe and the like raging reproaches, repreſenting them the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Proteſtants, as if our Prelatical Clergy were (as they are ſuſpected to be) the faſt friends <hi>to Papacy, and Roman Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure (my Lord) this perſon of quality never heard of <hi>Cranmer, Bancrofts, Hall, Moreton, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Davenant,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43230:6"/> Downam, and many other Prelates,</hi> who were anti-Presbyters, and yet by pen and pulpit preſſed, <hi>No peace with</hi> Rome: It is, Sir, the ſtrength of ſchiſm, to ſuggeſt and give men cauſe to ſuppoſe, our ſuppreſſion thereof, is the ſtriking hands with ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>My Lord, when Presbyters are out of play, I hope the Papiſts ſhall finde the Proteſtants ſpirit abide on the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who will not ceaſe from their pulpits and preſſes to declare, That <hi>Papiſts or Roman Catholicks</hi> qua tales <hi>believing and affirming no faith is to be kept with Hereticks (as they account all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants:) That the Pope is in all things to be obeyed, as a power abſolute and infallible: That the Pope may and can diſpence with, and abſolve all oathes, civil or religious obligations (the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinews of humane ſociety:) That he is Chriſts Vicar, and as ſuch, hath the univerſal power of the Kingdoms of the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, and may give them to whom he will: That the Popes Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication diſchargeth all natural and civil relation, and the duties thereof; abſolveth the ſubjects from allegiance to their lawful and natural Prince; warranteth the ſubjects rebellion, or neighbours invaſion and uſurpation: That the Pope may pard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n an impiety pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed, before it be perpetrated;</hi> as he did to the Monk which poyſoned King <hi>John,</hi> and the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators in the Gunpowder Treaſon againſt King <hi>James</hi> (all which muſt be moſt ſeriouſly abjured, without a Popiſh mental reſervation, before this Advocates ſecurity, <hi>That the Pope himſelf ſhall never be able to withdraw his clients from their allegiance to His ſacred Majeſtie, can he taken, or of force) are altogether inſociable, and cannot live with us, or any Proteſtants, with the ſafety of humane ſociety, which is more then jars and tumults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if, my Lord, <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> be found to be brats of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and children of Antichriſt, believing and practicing damnable Doctrines, and deceiving, unto the deſtruction of ſuch as drink their poyſons; from whom the Elect of God (having their names written in the Book of Life) are required to depart. They will not fear to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43230:7"/> that to <hi>give them the leaſt connivance, is no leſs then damnable</hi> (for our Church knoweth no venial ſin) and yet acquit themſelves from the charge of <hi>gall, ſpleen, madneſs, turbulency, extravagant heat, indiſcreet and hair-brained zeal,</hi> and the like epithetes framed out by this Supplicant; whoſe wiſdom it had been by ſofter words, and ſtronger reaſons to convince mens judgements, and perſwade the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of his party, in whoſe behalf he paſſeth from his paſſion, to offer ſomething to ſalve the inſolvible objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt their defired liberty.</p>
            <p>His firſt anſwer is, my Lord, according to the ſubtilty of the Man of ſin, urged with a double Sophiſm, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us for the demonſtration of the <hi>Papiſts ſociabilty,</hi> unto the times and places where and when Popery was predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; and bauking their barbarous cruelty, witneſſed by the bloody and inhumane perſecution of thoſe few Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs thoſe dark times afforded, he hath the confidence to tell your Lordſhip, <hi>That from the Saxons, to King</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, to be a Roman Catholick, was never a bar to loyalty, obedience to civil Government; nor can any deny, but that</hi> France, Spain, Italy, <hi>the Empire, and</hi> Poland, <hi>have ever accounted, and do ſtill him, as the beſt ſubject, and leaſt dangerous to the civil ſtate, who is beſt affected to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, this Advocate dealeth wiſely to appeal to thoſe times and places in which the ignorant devotion to S. <hi>Peters Keys,</hi> or awful dread of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſword, made Prince, themſelves moſt ſlaviſh Vaſſals to the Papacy, to take their Crowns at the Popes courteſie, and let his holineſs kick them off at his will, to dance attendance at the gates of <hi>Canuſium,</hi> or ſuffer themſelves to be whipt at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or his Holineſs to tread on their Royal necks, and give their Crowns to whom he pleaſeth; in which caſe they durſt not but deem the peoples affection to that power (to which themſelves ſwore allegiance) to be the beſt mark of loyalty; the very thoughts to the contrary being an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie worthy the Popes curſe, and loſs of their Crown: But
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43230:7"/> my Lord, one inſtance of a Prince fully freed from this Tyrannical yoke, would be much more convincing.</p>
            <p>But (my Lord) this Suppliant is ſure a ſtranger to the baſe and barbarous uſage of the Emperours <hi>Henrious</hi> the fourth and fifth, <hi>Fredericus Barbaroſſa,</hi> and <hi>Fredericus ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, Childericus</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> our own <hi>William Rufus,</hi> King <hi>John,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and others, with the commotions, perturbations, invaſions, uſurpations and rebellions againſt them, and many other Princes, made by and upon a blinde obedience of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> at the command of their holy Father the Pope; or thinks he, the ſound here of never reacht to <hi>England,</hi> or would he have <hi>Pipinus, Rodulphus, Anſelm, Thomas Becket,</hi> and the Clergy under <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, accounted moſt ſociable men, and loyal ſubjects, that he can with this confidence affirm, <hi>That from the Saxons times, unto King</hi> Edward <hi>the fixth, to be a</hi> Roman Catholick, <hi>was the beſt mark of loyalty:</hi> without doubt he hoped, that on the repeal of the <hi>Pepal Laws</hi> againſt the Papiſts, the Statute of the <hi>ſubmiſſion of the Clergy</hi> will meet with <hi>cui index expurgatorius,</hi> and that monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Roman Catholick diſloyalty be quite obliterated.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I wonder not ſo much to obſerve this perſon of quality to be miſtaken in the ſtate and demeanors of his Roman Catholicks in time long paſt, and forreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, as that he ſhould aver, <hi>That they have not at any time ſince been diſcovered, detected and charged with any imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, noxious to the civol State and Government of</hi> England; <note place="margin">pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>or that they did knit themſelves on any account of diſturbance here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure (my Lord) this Suppliant ſuppoſeth the <hi>Yorkshire, Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire, Norfolk, Suffolk, Cornwal,</hi> and <hi>Devonſhire</hi> rebellions <hi>againſt King</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth;</hi> the inſurrections, rebellions, commotions, plots and conſpiracies againſt Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> the conſpiracy and combination in the Gunpowder plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt King <hi>James,</hi> the late horrid Iriſh rebellion againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, to have been meer fictions, and falſe vanities, or not to have been tranfacted by Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, or to have been without diſturbance to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43230:8"/> in true allegiance to the King. But (my Lord) ſo zealous in his Clients cauſe is this Advocate, that he with confidence proceeds to avouch it, <hi>To the eternal glory of that truly noble and honourable party, that not one</hi> Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>of conſideration, was in Arms againſt His Majeſtie or His Father.</hi> Of whom thoſe Armies were conſtituted, I know not, nor is it a ſeaſon now to enquire: but this I know, there were many (who were no fools) that have obſerved (on grounds that I cannot avoid) that the Papiſts did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly, as well as eventually appear againſt, in appearing for his late Majeſtie, purſuing the plot managed by Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Barbarino</hi> and <hi>Curenus;</hi> and this I am ſure of, that they reap little honor by this bravado, who contradicteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, avouching here, <hi>not one in Arms againſt the King;</hi> and yet in his poſtſcript he tells your Lordſhip, <hi>Sir</hi> Arthur Aſhton <hi>had a commiſſion from the Rebels party;</hi> as (contrary to His Majeſties gracious Act of Oblivion) doth denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them: he will do well to winde off, by telling your Lordſhip Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was a man of <hi>no conſideration,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he will appear a right imp of Antichriſt, working, by lyes: One he tells ſo loudly in his poſtſcript, that all that ever knew the temper of what he calls that <hi>Presbyterian Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> muſt conclude it improbable, yea impoſſible, that after their diſcriminating Proteſtation, they ſhould <hi>extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly court the Papiſts to ſide with them, with a promiſe or proffer of the perfect Abolition of the Penal Laws:</hi> but wiſe men ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all debates about the unhappy war. This Advocate feeling his reaſon fail, forceth it up with rage at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorian party, as if Cathedral men were clearly <hi>Romes</hi> children: of that I have ſaid enough <hi>verbum ſat ſapienti.</hi> That we have had changes in Religion ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth his time, is not denyed, though bleſſed be God it hath been generally thought with ſome violent interruption (by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and ſchiſm, two extremes of an happy, hopeful Reformation) for the better. As to his Memento, we ſhall not deny it, becauſe we deſire it, <hi>viz. That they that are now</hi> in gloria Patri, may be hereafter <hi>ſicut erat in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43230:8"/> for if Rome will reurn to its primitive conſtitution, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline; as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> left her, I dare undertake ſhe will renounce her Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique maternity; and the very contemned Conſiſtorians, will embrace her as a Siſter, for that Superiority and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition which now ſwelleth her, were not (it is known) at the beginning.</p>
            <p>His caution we accept as good, and do deſire <hi>to continue and live ſo with all men in Chriſtian charity, and amity, as to forget that the bonds of religious unity, are ſet to be ſtrengthned as that the bonds of humane ſociety be not diſſolved;</hi> in purſuit whereof the duty of <hi>ſeparatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the man of ſin, and mother of abomination</hi> (from which Rome and her Papacy are not acquitted) and the <hi>inſociable principles and practiſes,</hi> openly expreſſed and ſadly experienced in theſe Kingdoms, doth ſtand againſt his deſired <hi>liberty,</hi> and render ineffectual all the inſtances of <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>Zwinglians</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> or <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the like (whoſe neceſſity or policy prompting the ſame we will not diſpute until he hath cleared the parallel, as well on the part of the indulged, as indulgents; and <hi>yet England will not degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from its antient glory and vertue, whilſt policy (the onely plea he maketh for their Spaniſh inquiſition cruelty)</hi> doth (as himſelf confeſſeth) teach more to keep <hi>faſt and firm to one Religion, and keep out deverſities of Religion,</hi> and (my Lord let me humbly add) <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> of <hi>readmitting that which hath been exiled, and Exploded and returneth with principles in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent to the common ſecurity of humane ſociety;</hi> My Lord not only nature but alſo Scripture doth dictate a <hi>jus talionis,</hi> to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and direct us to reward her, as ſhe hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded us.</p>
            <p>This Advocate having baracado'd the ſociability of his <hi>Roman Chatholiques;</hi> proceedeth to obviate one objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more; which he apprehendeth, and by his own fancy forceth to look big upon him: againſt which he fighteth with the hight of fury, not onely againſt a Conſiſtorian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43230:9"/> faction, but alſo the very conſtitution of the Nation: The objection he thus ſtates, <hi>It is not for their Religion, that Preiſts and their entertainers ſuffer but plain matter of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> unto this in heat of paſſion he Queries, <hi>how it comes to paſs, that it ſhould be treaſon to be a Prieſt? or Capital for a Gentleman to entertain him?</hi> and ſo raging at renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and againſt the Laws of our Nation, he tels your Lordſhip that this is not <hi>malum in ſe</hi> but <hi>quia prohibitum;</hi> but no way denyeth or avoideth the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſpends this whole paragraph in fretting againſt the Law, and Law-maker: in which I deſire your Lordſhip will pleaſe to note.</p>
            <p>The <hi>arrogancy of this Advocate, whoſe</hi> angry words do beſpeak him and his party prompt to blows; (if the time would permit it) he pretendeth to beg for liberty, and yet preſumeth to arraign the very <hi>Law</hi> (deſired to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed) at the bar of his own private fancy; and chargeth the Law, and Law-makers, with <hi>irrationallity and injuſtice,</hi> or at <hi>leaſt ſtrange ſeverities;</hi> and that becauſe this treaſon becomes ſuch <hi>quia prohibitum;</hi> and if legiſlation did not poſſeſs a power, to make a Capital crime of that Act which is not <hi>malum in ſe:</hi> was it my Lord <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> to pray (in ſence of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> cruel and perſecuting diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) <hi>that the Lord would turn her heart, or take her out of this World,</hi> and yet may I not ask this Advocate how it became Treaſon ſo to pray; was it not <hi>quia prohibitum,</hi> my Lord, theſe Roman Catholiques, who without Law or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can make truth <hi>bonum in ſe,</hi> Hereſie to be puniſhed with fire, <hi>quia eſt contra, catholicam (viz) Romanam,</hi> though not barred by any law cannot brook a Treaſon <hi>quia prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum;</hi> how many of our Laws will be levelled, and laid aſide, if this mans exception may be admitted, and how muſt legiſlators give an account of the nature of every act which occaſioneth them to give it that name of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet if this advocate had pleaſed to conſider the Law he might have ſeen a <hi>proditorious appeal, and ſubjection to, and</hi> advancement of a forraign power and potentate, over
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43230:9"/> and oppoſite to the Soveraign Majeſtie of this Kingdom in every Roman Popiſh Prieſt; and there is the <hi>Rati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis</hi> of the Treaſon, and makes it ſuch <hi>quia malum in ſe,</hi> as well as <hi>quia prohibitum.</hi> But (my Lord) that which ſticks in the ſtomack of theſe Romen Catholicks is, the <hi>power of which their Prieſts are deprived.</hi> He tells your Lordſhip, <hi>The Prieſts were wont here in</hi> England <hi>to ſit in the chair of Government, and by their Oracles and Decrees, the people of this Land were onely wont to he directed both in Chancery, Rolls, and Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi> You may ſee my Lord, to what pitch the Roman Catholicks would ſcrew their deſired liberty, that the <hi>to eſse</hi> of our Laws may depend on their Prieſts <hi>Anathema;</hi> the places of truſt and honor be by them poſſeſſed, judgement be by them diſpenced, and all civil Offices be at their command, to commend their ſociabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by executing the writ <hi>de Hereticus comburendis,</hi> on the bare ſay of a Prieſt, that this man is an Heretick. My Lord, all Lawyers that lay away this liberty, are ſtrange and irrational, and deſired to be repealed.</p>
            <p>2. My Lord, the <hi>little reaſon</hi> of this Corrector of the reaſon of our Law, is worth obſervation: In his blinde paſſion, he ſuppoſeth and ſuggeſteth it to be made treaſon <hi>to be a Prieſt,</hi> and manageth all his invectives againſt the Law, as if it were againſt the name Prieſt; which in its general nature, and vulgar acceptation denoteth, <hi>cui admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator of holy things between God and his people:</hi> And ſo we know <hi>Moſes</hi> conſecrated a Prieſt. Chriſt was and is a Prieſt; our Church call Miniſters Prieſts, and every true Saint is a Prieſt; and the Law muſt needs ſeem unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that ſhall make <hi>it Treaſon</hi> for a man to be a Prieſt, in ſo large a ſenſe as he by an <hi>ignoratio Elenchi</hi> renders it; but could his heat have admitted him to have caſt an eye on the Statute, he would have found the Traytors to have <hi>been Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, or other Prieſts, made or ordained out of the Realm, or in the Realm, by any power, authority, or juriſdiction, derived, challenged or pretended from the ſea of</hi> Rome; And ſo the Treaſon to conſiſt not in their being
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43230:10"/> ſimple Prieſts, but in their being <hi>Roman Prieſts,</hi> ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, and advancing a Forreign Power and Authority above their natural Prince: He may, my Lord, on enquiry, finde <hi>Prieſts,</hi> yea <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> when converted from the Papacy, have enjoyed the liberty of Subjects, and not been judged Traytors, though he profoundly fancieth the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be in the general appellation; and as ſuch, ſcolds at the Law as unreaſonable, and ſo runs into the third miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor to be obſerved; <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>His in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olency,</hi> in preſuming to reproach the renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as <hi>illegitimate, and an uſurper of the Crown:</hi> and ſo charging theſe Laws to have been the products of her <hi>fears and jealouſies</hi> againſt <hi>Mary Queen of Scots,</hi> whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to have been the <hi>juſt heir of the Crown:</hi> all which with a right Roman Catholick ſpirit, he bottometh <hi>on the Popes declaring her illegitimate:</hi> it is indeed true, he doth mention our own <hi>Acts of Parliaments,</hi> which did declare her ſuch; but, my Lord, his foundation is the <hi>Popes Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> and <hi>Cenſure;</hi> otherwiſe his argument were the ſame againſt Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who alſo was declared <hi>illegitimate;</hi> and he would have ſeen Acts of Parliament appropriating the Crown to her, as well as they had ſometime taken it from her. My Lord, come not the the Roman Catholicks with a very ſubmiſſive ſpirit to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate their liberty, thus to reproach our Princes and Laws, and ſo demanding the repeal of Penal Laws againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as a matter due and juſt: But if, my Lord, tha <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> were the onely rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and cauſe of thoſe Statutes, how was it that theſe laws did not ceaſe with their cauſe, after King <hi>James</hi> (right heir according to this Advocates account) come to the Crown? Theſe laws were not onely continued, but renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and rendred more ſevere, as the Catholick inſociability (manifeſted by their bloody and barbarous conſpiracies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, whom their Pope could not declare illegitimate) had conſtrained.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I have made bold to confider the Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43230:10"/> of this Advocate, for the toleration of Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks: The remaining part of his Book is but a Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical ſwada, in which there are many words and ſentences obnoxious to exception: but knowing that your Lordſhip is more judicious then to be courted by words without weight, I will not trouble your Lordſhip with any obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of them; but humbly commit the cauſe to your grand and pious conſideration, not doubting but your zeal to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the intereſt of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, honor of our King, and glory of our Church (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ruined by Sciſmaticks, on a ſuſpicion that it would ſtrike hands with Roman Catholicks) will prove more fervent, then to be extinguiſhed or abated by the water of theſe falſe ſuggeſtions, furious expoſtulations, or fair ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken perſwaſions; and that your Lordſhip will never engage your ſelf, to indulge an intereſt directly contrary to our Laws, Church, Religion, and Scripture duty: In which confidence I commend your Lordſhip unto the Grace that is able, and will eſtabliſh you to the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordsſhips moſt devoted hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant, <hi>C. D.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 8. 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
